<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://bvolkangurses.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://bvolkangurses.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-11-19T21:27:15+00:00</updated><id>https://bvolkangurses.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Volkan Gurses</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Fundamental physical limits of technologies</title><link href="https://bvolkangurses.github.io/blog/2025/technology-limits/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fundamental physical limits of technologies"/><published>2025-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://bvolkangurses.github.io/blog/2025/technology-limits</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bvolkangurses.github.io/blog/2025/technology-limits/"><![CDATA[<p>Technologies leverage discoveries in fundamental sciences for practical purposes, enabling applications not previously attainable. Due to this foundation in fundamental sciences, all technologies have limits bounded by physics. Especially with the dizzying accelerating advancements, technologies can make it seem like they can make anything possible. However, these fundamental physical limits determine the boundaries in performance of all technologies.</p> <p>Identifying these boundaries is a fruitful endeavor. It enables three things:</p> <ol> <li>It allows us to know how far we can go before we are limited by our understanding of nature.</li> <li>It allows us to understand why our current technologies can’t perform better.</li> <li>It allows us to understand what we can do to make our technologies better.</li> </ol> <p>To delineate fundamental physical limits of technologies, we need to start with delineating technologies themselves. Information technologies can be categorized into three groups based on their application domain:</p> <ol> <li>Computing technologies</li> <li>Communication technologies</li> <li>Sensing/metrology technologies.</li> </ol> <p>All of them are self-explanatory, but it is helpful to categorize them clearly so that we can clarify the thought processes that go into inventing new technologies in these domains. Ways these technologies handle information are also similar enough that a lot of the limits arising in pushing these technologies are coupled to one another. However, we will categorize these limits so that each limit is a dominant boundary for the way their performances are determined.</p> <p><strong>Fundamental physical limits</strong></p> <p>There are various fundamental physical limits arising from quantum field theory and general relativity. There is only so much information you can squeeze into a space before it collapses into a black hole. There is only so much you can localize a particle before intrinsic uncertainty from quantum mechanics stop you from deciding where it is. We will untangle these general bounds in fundamental physics and assign them into their corresponding technology domain.</p> <p><strong>Computing limits</strong></p> <p>Computing is limited by the Bekenstein limit, quantum speed limit, Landauer limit.</p> <p><strong>Communication limits</strong></p> <p>Communication is limited by the Holevo limit, speed of light limit.</p> <p><strong>Sensing limits</strong></p> <p>Sensing is limited by the Heisenberg limit.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="physics,"/><category term="technology,"/><category term="engineering,"/><category term="future"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[why we should study the fundamental physical limits of technologies]]></summary></entry></feed>